
import { MCQ } from '@/lib/types';
import { shortQuestions as shortQuestionsData } from './computer-short-questions';
import { longQuestions as longQuestionsData } from './computer-long-questions';

export const chapters = [
  "Emerging Technologies",
  "Data Communication and Computer Networks",
  "Microsoft Excel",
  "Google Sheets",
  "Computational Thinking",
  "Programming",
  "Digital Citizenship",
  "Entrepreneurship in Digital Age",
];

export const mcqs: Record<string, MCQ[]> = {
  "Emerging Technologies": [
    { "id": 1, "questionText": "Which of the following describes emerging technologies?", "options": ["Technology that is no longer in use.", "New technology that is still under development and will replace current technologies.", "Technology that is limited to a single field.", "Technology that has been around for decades."], "correctAnswer": "New technology that is still under development and will replace current technologies." },
    { "id": 2, "questionText": "The branch of engineering that uses intelligent machines to assist humans in different tasks is called:", "options": ["Artificial Intelligence", "Blockchain", "Robotics", "5G"], "correctAnswer": "Robotics" },
    { "id": 3, "questionText": "Robots are used in which of the following areas?", "options": ["Manufacturing", "Mining", "Logistics", "All of the above"], "correctAnswer": "All of the above" },
    { "id": 4, "questionText": "What is the meaning of the Czech word \"robota,\" which is the source of the English term \"robot\"?", "options": ["Intelligent machine", "Hard work", "Automated helper", "Humanoid"], "correctAnswer": "Hard work" },
    { "id": 5, "questionText": "Artificial Intelligence (AI) is a branch of Computer Science that deals with building smart machines capable of performing tasks intelligently, often learning from their own experiences. What is AI?", "options": ["A type of network", "A programming language", "A branch of Computer Science", "A database system"], "correctAnswer": "A branch of Computer Science" },
    { "id": 6, "questionText": "Which of the following are applications of Artificial Intelligence?", "options": ["Machine vision", "Expert systems", "Chatbots", "All of the above"], "correctAnswer": "All of the above" },
    { "id": 7, "questionText": "A self-driving car is also known as a(n):", "options": ["Remote-controlled vehicle", "Autonomous vehicle", "Manual vehicle", "Electric vehicle"], "correctAnswer": "Autonomous vehicle" },
    { "id": 8, "questionText": "Self-driving cars use a variety of sensors such as:", "options": ["Thermographic cameras", "Radar", "GPS", "All of the above"], "correctAnswer": "All of the above" },
    { "id": 9, "questionText": "What does VR stand for in emerging technologies?", "options": ["Virtual Reality Visualisation", "Visual Recognition", "Virtual Reality", "Voice Recognition"], "correctAnswer": "Virtual Reality" },
    { "id": 10, "questionText": "A VR application can be downloaded from:", "options": ["Apple Store", "Google Play Store", "Microsoft Store", "Amazon Appstore"], "correctAnswer": "Google Play Store" },
    { "id": 11, "questionText": "Virtual reality is a computer-generated imitation of a real-world environment. Which of the following is true about VR?", "options": ["It creates a natural environment", "It is also known as Augmented Reality", "It is a computer-generated imitation", "It is a type of 3D imaging"], "correctAnswer": "It is a computer-generated imitation" },
    { "id": 12, "questionText": "What technology uses digital and three-dimensional (3D) components to merge with the real world?", "options": ["Virtual Reality", "Augmented Reality", "Mixed Reality", "Holographic Imaging"], "correctAnswer": "Augmented Reality" },
    { "id": 13, "questionText": "In which industries is Augmented Reality (AR) used?", "options": ["Gaming", "Medical field training", "Public safety education", "All of the above"], "correctAnswer": "All of the above" },
    { "id": 14, "questionText": "Distributed applications are those that operate simultaneously on several different computers, with systems operating on the network and communicating to complete a task. What is another name for this?", "options": ["Centralized applications", "Local applications", "Distributed Systems", "Standalone applications"], "correctAnswer": "Distributed Systems" },
    { "id": 15, "questionText": "What is a method of storing data in blocks that makes it difficult to change or hack?", "options": ["Database", "Blockchain", "Server", "Cloud Storage"], "correctAnswer": "Blockchain" },
    { "id": 16, "questionText": "Blockchain technology is used to innovate games, secure healthcare data, and provide transparency for:", "options": ["Business", "Financial services", "Market trends", "All of the above"], "correctAnswer": "All of the above" },
    { "id": 17, "questionText": "Which technology is a branch of artificial intelligence that enables a system to learn and improve itself from its experience without any user interference?", "options": ["Robotics", "Machine Learning", "Blockchain", "5G"], "correctAnswer": "Machine Learning" },
    { "id": 18, "questionText": "Machine learning deals with the development of computer programs that can access data (training data) and use it to:", "options": ["Store data", "Create new data", "Learn for themselves", "Transfer data"], "correctAnswer": "Learn for themselves" },
    { "id": 19, "questionText": "What does 5G stand for?", "options": ["Fifth Generation of Computer Graphics", "Fifth Generation of Cellular Technology", "Fifth Generation of Computer Software", "Fifth Generation of Communication"], "correctAnswer": "Fifth Generation of Cellular Technology" },
    { "id": 20, "questionText": "Compared to earlier generations, 5G technology offers:", "options": ["Less speed", "More data delays", "More flexible and less data transfer delays", "Limited coverage"], "correctAnswer": "More flexible and less data transfer delays" },
    { "id": 21, "questionText": "Applications of 5G technology include:", "options": ["Autonomous vehicles", "Video games", "Smart farming", "All of the above"], "correctAnswer": "All of the above" },
    { "id": 22, "questionText": "What is Computer Assisted Translation (CAT)?", "options": ["A software for graphic design", "Software programs that translate written and spoken texts from one language to another", "A program for computer programming", "A system for data analysis"], "correctAnswer": "Software programs that translate written and spoken texts from one language to another" },
    { "id": 23, "questionText": "CAT speeds up lengthy translations, reduces errors, and is affordable. It uses Language Service Providers (LSPs), translation and localisation companies, independent translators, and:", "options": ["Artificial Intelligence", "Multilingual workers", "Machine Learning", "Neural Networks"], "correctAnswer": "Multilingual workers" },
    { "id": 24, "questionText": "Which company provides an example of Computer Assisted Translation?", "options": ["Microsoft", "Apple", "Google", "IBM"], "correctAnswer": "Google" },
    { "id": 25, "questionText": "Which of the following is generally referred to as 'Emerging Technology'?", "options": ["Old technology", "Discontinued development", "New technology", "Best technology"], "correctAnswer": "New technology" },
    { "id": 26, "questionText": "Which of the following is not an example of an emerging technology?", "options": ["Virtual Reality", "Blockchain", "Robotics", "3G"], "correctAnswer": "3G" },
    { "id": 27, "questionText": "What is a computer-generated imitation of the real-world where people can interact in an apparently real or physical way?", "options": ["Virtual Reality", "Augmented Reality", "Mixed Reality", "Holographic Imaging"], "correctAnswer": "Virtual Reality" },
    { "id": 28, "questionText": "Distributed applications are those that operate simultaneously on several different computers. What are these applications called?", "options": ["Embedded", "Virtual", "Distributed", "None of these"], "correctAnswer": "Distributed" },
    { "id": 29, "questionText": "In a blockchain system, the transaction or file recorded cannot be:", "options": ["opened", "read", "saved", "modified"], "correctAnswer": "modified" },
    { "id": 30, "questionText": "The estimated data rate of 5G technology is:", "options": ["10Gbps", "15Gbps", "20Gbps", "25Gbps"], "correctAnswer": "20Gbps" },
    { "id": 31, "questionText": "What is a branch of Artificial Intelligence that enables a system to learn and improve itself from its experience without any user interference?", "options": ["Blockchain", "Machine Learning", "Virtual Reality", "None of these"], "correctAnswer": "Machine Learning" },
    { "id": 32, "questionText": "Which of the following is an example of a chatbot?", "options": ["Blockchain", "Robotics", "Artificial Intelligence", "Augmented Reality"], "correctAnswer": "Artificial Intelligence" },
    { "id": 33, "questionText": "What is CAT also known as?", "options": ["Computer Assisted Translation", "Computer Automated Translation", "Computer Aided Translation", "Computer Application Translation"], "correctAnswer": "Computer Aided Translation" },
    { "id": 34, "questionText": "A self-driving car is also known as:", "options": ["Autonomous vehicle", "Driverless car", "Robotic car", "All of these"], "correctAnswer": "All of these" },
    { "id": 35, "questionText": "Absolute technology is generally referred to as 'Emerging Technology.'", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "False" },
    { "id": 36, "questionText": "A self-driving car is also known as a manual vehicle.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "False" },
    { "id": 37, "questionText": "Virtual Reality is a technology that creates a natural environment.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "False" },
    { "id": 38, "questionText": "Robotics is replacing human efforts.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "True" },
    { "id": 39, "questionText": "Virtual Reality is 3D imaging.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "False" },
    { "id": 40, "questionText": "Virtual Reality is the same as Augmented Reality.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "False" },
    { "id": 41, "questionText": "Machine Learning is a system that improves itself with experience.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "True" },
    { "id": 42, "questionText": "What is meant by Augmented Reality?", "options": ["A virtual world", "A computer-generated imitation", "Merging digital and three-dimensional components with the real world", "A self-driving car"], "correctAnswer": "Merging digital and three-dimensional components with the real world" },
    { "id": 43, "questionText": "What are some of the applications of AI?", "options": ["Robotics", "Chatbots", "Machine Vision", "All of the above"], "correctAnswer": "All of the above" },
    { "id": 44, "questionText": "What is holographic imaging?", "options": ["2D imaging", "3D imaging", "Virtual reality", "Augmented reality"], "correctAnswer": "3D imaging" },
    { "id": 45, "questionText": "What are the primary difficulties in robotics?", "options": ["Cost of production", "Lack of skilled labor", "Intelligent machines cannot perform various tasks without human interference", "Energy consumption"], "correctAnswer": "Intelligent machines cannot perform various tasks without human interference" },
    { "id": 46, "questionText": "What are the other names used for self-driving cars?", "options": ["Driverless cars", "Autonomous vehicles", "Robotic cars", "All of the above"], "correctAnswer": "All of the above" },
    { "id": 47, "questionText": "State the applications of 3D imaging.", "options": ["Virtual Reality", "Augmented Reality", "Holographic Imaging", "All of the above"], "correctAnswer": "All of the above" },
    { "id": 48, "questionText": "Which device is used to experience virtual reality?", "options": ["Smartphone", "Computer monitor", "VR Headset", "Tablet"], "correctAnswer": "VR Headset" },
    { "id": 49, "questionText": "Blockchain is a method of storing data in blocks that makes it difficult or even impossible to change the data or hack it. What is blockchain?", "options": ["A type of network", "A database", "A method of storing data in blocks", "A programming paradigm"], "correctAnswer": "A method of storing data in blocks" },
    { "id": 50, "questionText": "The number of AR application cases is rapidly expanding. The AR industry is anticipated to be valued more than $18 billion in which year?", "options": ["2021", "2022", "2023", "2024"], "correctAnswer": "2023" }
  ],
  "Data Communication and Computer Networks": [
    { "id": 1, "questionText": "What is the process of sending and receiving data electronically from one location to another?", "options": ["Networking", "Internet", "Data Communication", "Telecommunication"], "correctAnswer": "Data Communication" },
    { "id": 2, "questionText": "Data can be transferred using which of the following?", "options": ["Wired media", "Wireless media", "Optical media", "Both a and b"], "correctAnswer": "Both a and b" },
    { "id": 3, "questionText": "Which of the following are the main components of a data communication system?", "options": ["Message", "Sender", "Receiver", "All of the above"], "correctAnswer": "All of the above" },
    { "id": 4, "questionText": "In a data communication system, what is the information that needs to be sent?", "options": ["Sender", "Receiver", "Message", "Transmission Media"], "correctAnswer": "Message" },
    { "id": 5, "questionText": "A computer or device that sends a message is called a:", "options": ["Receiver", "Sender", "Message", "Encoder"], "correctAnswer": "Sender" },
    { "id": 6, "questionText": "A computer or a device that receives a message is called a:", "options": ["Sender", "Receiver", "Message", "Decoder"], "correctAnswer": "Receiver" },
    { "id": 7, "questionText": "What is the path on which a message travels from the sender to the receiver?", "options": ["Channel", "Network", "Transmission Media", "Data Link"], "correctAnswer": "Transmission Media" },
    { "id": 8, "questionText": "Devices that convert digital signals into a form that can travel over wired or wireless media are called:", "options": ["Receivers", "Senders", "Encoders and Decoders", "Transmitters"], "correctAnswer": "Encoders and Decoders" },
    { "id": 9, "questionText": "Which type of transmission media is a physical path over which a signal transmits?", "options": ["Wireless media", "Physical Transmission Media", "Optical media", "Virtual media"], "correctAnswer": "Physical Transmission Media" },
    { "id": 10, "questionText": "Guided Media and Bounded Media are different types of:", "options": ["Wireless transmission media", "Physical transmission media", "Computer networks", "Data communication systems"], "correctAnswer": "Physical transmission media" },
    { "id": 11, "questionText": "Twisted pair cable is a type of physical media that is:", "options": ["Not commonly used", "Expensive", "Commonly used", "Difficult to install"], "correctAnswer": "Commonly used" },
    { "id": 12, "questionText": "A twisted pair cable is made by twisting two separate insulated wires together to:", "options": ["Increase weight", "Reduce cost", "Reduce transmission noise", "Increase flexibility"], "correctAnswer": "Reduce transmission noise" },
    { "id": 13, "questionText": "Which of the following is an advantage of twisted pair cable?", "options": ["High bandwidth", "Long distances", "Relatively easy to implement and terminate", "Immunity to EMI"], "correctAnswer": "Relatively easy to implement and terminate" },
    { "id": 14, "questionText": "Which of the following is a disadvantage of twisted pair cable?", "options": ["Low in weight", "Flexible to use", "Easy to connect", "Susceptible to electromagnetic interference (EMI)"], "correctAnswer": "Susceptible to electromagnetic interference (EMI)" },
    { "id": 15, "questionText": "Coaxial cable consists of a single copper wire surrounded by at least how many layers?", "options": ["One", "Two", "Three", "Four"], "correctAnswer": "Three" },
    { "id": 16, "questionText": "Compared to twisted pair cable, coaxial cable has a higher data transmission rate and is commonly used for:", "options": ["Telephone lines", "Internet access", "CATV network cabling", "Satellite communication"], "correctAnswer": "CATV network cabling" },
    { "id": 17, "questionText": "Which of the following is an advantage of coaxial cable?", "options": ["Less expensive compared to twisted pair cable", "Prone to noise", "Enhanced shielding as compared to twisted pair cable", "Difficult to connect"], "correctAnswer": "Enhanced shielding as compared to twisted pair cable" },
    { "id": 18, "questionText": "Which of the following is a disadvantage of coaxial cable?", "options": ["Higher data transmission rate", "Provides more bandwidth", "Enhanced shielding", "More expensive compared to a twisted pair cable"], "correctAnswer": "More expensive compared to a twisted pair cable" },
    { "id": 19, "questionText": "A fiber-optic cable's core is made up of many small, light-transmitting glass, plastic, or silica fibers. What is the core material?", "options": ["Copper", "Aluminum", "Glass, plastic, or silica fibers", "Rubber"], "correctAnswer": "Glass, plastic, or silica fibers" },
    { "id": 20, "questionText": "Which type of cable offers the highest bandwidth and transmits data at a higher rate?", "options": ["Twisted pair cable", "Coaxial cable", "Fiber optic cable", "Ethernet cable"], "correctAnswer": "Fiber optic cable" },
    { "id": 21, "questionText": "Which of the following are advantages of fiber optic cable?", "options": ["Provides more bandwidth", "Data travels at longer distances", "Is resistant to any temperature changes", "All of the above"], "correctAnswer": "All of the above" },
    { "id": 22, "questionText": "Which of the following is a disadvantage of fiber optic cable?", "options": ["Cables are costly", "Difficult to connect with other devices", "Installation is difficult because of its delicate nature", "All of the above"], "correctAnswer": "All of the above" },
    { "id": 23, "questionText": "A Wi-Fi network is simply an internet connection that is shared with multiple devices in a home or business via a wireless router. What does Wi-Fi stand for?", "options": ["Wireless Field", "Wireless Fidelity", "Wide Field", "Wired Fidelity"], "correctAnswer": "Wireless Fidelity" },
    { "id": 24, "questionText": "Li-Fi is a wireless optical networking technology that uses LEDs for data transmission. What does Li-Fi stand for?", "options": ["Light Field", "Light Fidelity", "Laser Fidelity", "Link Fidelity"], "correctAnswer": "Light Fidelity" },
    { "id": 25, "questionText": "Li-Fi transmission speeds can go over 100 Gbps, which is how many times faster than the world's fastest Wi-Fi?", "options": ["10 times", "50 times", "100 times", "1000 times"], "correctAnswer": "100 times" },
    { "id": 26, "questionText": "Which of the following are wireless transmission services?", "options": ["Cellular Communication", "Satellite Communication", "Global Positioning System", "All of the above"], "correctAnswer": "All of the above" },
    { "id": 27, "questionText": "A cellular network is a radio network distributed over a vast area through hexagonal cells. Each cell in this network includes a fixed location transceiver known as the:", "options": ["Mobile device", "Satellite", "Base station", "Router"], "correctAnswer": "Base station" },
    { "id": 28, "questionText": "What system provides worldwide coverage for telecommunication, television transmission, and other wireless services?", "options": ["Cellular Communication", "Satellite Communication System", "Global Positioning System", "Bluetooth"], "correctAnswer": "Satellite Communication System" },
    { "id": 29, "questionText": "GPS is a subcategory of satellite communication. What does GPS stand for?", "options": ["General Positioning System", "Global Public System", "Global Positioning System", "Geographic Positioning Service"], "correctAnswer": "Global Positioning System" },
    { "id": 30, "questionText": "When was GPS first made available in automobiles?", "options": ["1986", "1996", "2006", "2016"], "correctAnswer": "1996" },
    { "id": 31, "questionText": "Bluetooth is another important low-range wireless communication system. It provides data, voice, and audio transmission with a transmission range of:", "options": ["1 meter", "5 meters", "10 meters", "100 meters"], "correctAnswer": "10 meters" },
    { "id": 32, "questionText": "In 1996, GPS initial applications were used for which purposes?", "options": ["Commercial use", "Personal navigation", "Military purposes", "Automotive industry"], "correctAnswer": "Military purposes" },
    { "id": 33, "questionText": "A computer network that connects two or more devices for sharing and transmitting information is called a:", "options": ["Server", "Router", "Computer Network", "Switch"], "correctAnswer": "Computer Network" },
    { "id": 34, "questionText": "LAN is a network that is restricted to a small geographical area, typically within a building or group of buildings. What does LAN stand for?", "options": ["Long Area Network", "Local Access Network", "Local Area Network", "Limited Area Network"], "correctAnswer": "Local Area Network" },
    { "id": 35, "questionText": "Which of the following is an advantage of a LAN?", "options": ["High cost", "Limited geographic area", "Data is saved centrally", "Difficult to manage"], "correctAnswer": "Data is saved centrally" },
    { "id": 36, "questionText": "Which of the following is a disadvantage of a LAN?", "options": ["Data is saved centrally", "Easy to spread virus", "The rate of data transfer is high", "Extremely high maintenance is required"], "correctAnswer": "Easy to spread virus" },
    { "id": 37, "questionText": "WAN spans a large geographic area, such as an entire city, region, or even an entire country or all over the world. What does WAN stand for?", "options": ["Wired Area Network", "Wireless Area Network", "Wide Area Network", "World Area Network"], "correctAnswer": "Wide Area Network" },
    { "id": 38, "questionText": "Which of the following is an advantage of a WAN?", "options": ["Slower speed", "High maintenance", "Covers large geographical area", "High setup cost"], "correctAnswer": "Covers large geographical area" },
    { "id": 39, "questionText": "Which of the following is a disadvantage of a WAN?", "options": ["Covers large geographical area", "Communication on WAN is simple", "Higher speed than LAN", "Its maintenance is extremely complex"], "correctAnswer": "Its maintenance is extremely complex" },
    { "id": 40, "questionText": "MAN connects local area networks in a city or town. What does MAN stand for?", "options": ["Mobile Area Network", "Main Area Network", "Metropolitan Access Network", "Metropolitan Area Network"], "correctAnswer": "Metropolitan Area Network" },
    { "id": 41, "questionText": "Which of the following is an advantage of a MAN?", "options": ["Slower data rate", "Expensive maintenance", "Offers greater security than a WAN", "For a MAN connection, one location to another, more cable is needed."], "correctAnswer": "Offers greater security than a WAN" },
    { "id": 42, "questionText": "What does VPN stand for?", "options": ["Virtual Public Network", "Verified Private Network", "Virtual Private Network", "Very Private Network"], "correctAnswer": "Virtual Private Network" },
    { "id": 43, "questionText": "A VPN creates a secure connection over the Internet from a device to a network, ensuring that sensitive data is safely transmitted. What is the purpose of VPN?", "options": ["To access public networks", "To increase internet speed", "To provide a secure connection over the Internet", "To block all internet traffic"], "correctAnswer": "To provide a secure connection over the Internet" },
    { "id": 44, "questionText": "IoT is a network of interconnected computing devices. What does IoT stand for?", "options": ["Internet on Things", "Internet of Things", "Information of Things", "Interconnected Objects"], "correctAnswer": "Internet of Things" },
    { "id": 45, "questionText": "Which of the following are examples of the Internet of Things (IoT)?", "options": ["Connected appliances", "Smart home security systems", "Wearable health monitors", "All of the above"], "correctAnswer": "All of the above" },
    { "id": 46, "questionText": "What is an Embedded Computer?", "options": ["A general-purpose computer", "A powerful server", "A dedicated computer system that is an essential component of a bigger machine or system", "A cloud computing device"], "correctAnswer": "A dedicated computer system that is an essential component of a bigger machine or system" },
    { "id": 47, "questionText": "Edge computing is a computing model that focuses on bringing computing devices and sources of data as closely as possible to improve response times and save bandwidth. Which of the following is true about Edge Computing?", "options": ["It requires long-distance communication.", "It always uses centralized servers.", "It brings computing devices closer to data sources.", "It is a type of data analysis."], "correctAnswer": "It brings computing devices closer to data sources." },
    { "id": 48, "questionText": "Which of the following are applications of Edge Computing?", "options": ["Autonomous vehicles", "Remote monitoring of assets in the oil and gas industry", "Cloud gaming", "All of the above"], "correctAnswer": "All of the above" },
    { "id": 49, "questionText": "Data Analytics is the science of analysing raw data to make assumptions about that information. Which of the following is true about Data Analytics?", "options": ["It is only used for data storage.", "It focuses on creating new data.", "It helps a business optimise its performance.", "It is a type of hardware."], "correctAnswer": "It helps a business optimise its performance." },
    { "id": 50, "questionText": "Which is a wireless optical networking technology that uses LEDs for data transmission?", "options": ["Wi-Fi", "Fiber optic cable", "Coaxial cable", "Li-Fi"], "correctAnswer": "Li-Fi" }
  ],
  "Microsoft Excel": [
    { "id": 1, "questionText": "Microsoft Excel is a type of:", "options": ["Word processing software", "Presentation software", "Spreadsheet software", "Database software"], "correctAnswer": "Spreadsheet software" },
    { "id": 2, "questionText": "Spreadsheets are used to:", "options": ["Write documents", "Create presentations", "Arrange, calculate, and sort data in the form of a table", "Store images"], "correctAnswer": "Arrange, calculate, and sort data in the form of a table" },
    { "id": 3, "questionText": "Spreadsheets are used for numerous purposes. The most common uses are as under:", "options": ["To store data in rows and columns", "To organise and store different types of data", "To perform calculations and computation of data", "All of the above"], "correctAnswer": "All of the above" },
    { "id": 4, "questionText": "What is the term for a single file in Excel that contains one or more worksheets?", "options": ["Worksheet", "Cell", "Range", "Workbook"], "correctAnswer": "Workbook" },
    { "id": 5, "questionText": "A grid of rows and columns where you enter data is called a:", "options": ["Workbook", "Chart", "Worksheet", "Cell Range"], "correctAnswer": "Worksheet" },
    { "id": 6, "questionText": "The intersection of a row and column in a worksheet is called a:", "options": ["Range", "Row", "Column", "Cell"], "correctAnswer": "Cell" },
    { "id": 7, "questionText": "The references of adjacent cells may be denoted as a:", "options": ["Cell", "Column", "Row", "Cell Range"], "correctAnswer": "Cell Range" },
    { "id": 8, "questionText": "The Excel interface contains many components like Ribbon, Quick Access Toolbar, Formula Bar, Status Bar, and your:", "options": ["Worksheet", "Workbook", "Spreadsheet Work Area", "Cell Range"], "correctAnswer": "Spreadsheet Work Area" },
    { "id": 9, "questionText": "Which of the following is frequently used in Excel and allows you to add or delete different tools?", "options": ["Ribbon", "Formula Bar", "Status Bar", "Quick Access Toolbar"], "correctAnswer": "Quick Access Toolbar" },
    { "id": 10, "questionText": "The ribbon contains the icons (or toolbars) for commands. These commands are grouped in different tabs based on their:", "options": ["Popularity", "Color", "Functionality", "Size"], "correctAnswer": "Functionality" },
    { "id": 11, "questionText": "Which tab in Excel is used to apply formats to worksheet cells, including editing, clipboard, font, alignment, number, and cells?", "options": ["Insert Tab", "Draw Tab", "Page Layout Tab", "Home Tab"], "correctAnswer": "Home Tab" },
    { "id": 12, "questionText": "Which tab is used to insert different objects in Excel, like images, hyperlinks, symbols, headers, and footers?", "options": ["Home Tab", "Insert Tab", "Data Tab", "Review Tab"], "correctAnswer": "Insert Tab" },
    { "id": 13, "questionText": "Which tab lets you draw with the help of a mouse, digital pen, etc.?", "options": ["Insert Tab", "Draw Tab", "View Tab", "Formulas Tab"], "correctAnswer": "Draw Tab" },
    { "id": 14, "questionText": "Which tab helps in changing the appearance of the worksheet, including gridlines, margins, and themes?", "options": ["Home Tab", "Data Tab", "Page Layout Tab", "Review Tab"], "correctAnswer": "Page Layout Tab" },
    { "id": 15, "questionText": "Which tab contains practical features for adding different calculations to the worksheet, used to insert functions, specify names, establish name ranges, and review formulas?", "options": ["Data Tab", "Review Tab", "View Tab", "Formulas Tab"], "correctAnswer": "Formulas Tab" },
    { "id": 16, "questionText": "Which tab offers options for filtering, sorting, and modifying data?", "options": ["Home Tab", "Insert Tab", "Data Tab", "View Tab"], "correctAnswer": "Data Tab" },
    { "id": 17, "questionText": "Which tab helps in reviewing the information like checking the spellings, translation, adding comments, etc.?", "options": ["Home Tab", "Data Tab", "Review Tab", "View Tab"], "correctAnswer": "Review Tab" },
    { "id": 18, "questionText": "Which tab includes commands that help in switching between the view of workbooks, freezing panes, adding macros, etc.?", "options": ["Review Tab", "Data Tab", "View Tab", "Home Tab"], "correctAnswer": "View Tab" },
    { "id": 19, "questionText": "The bar above the spreadsheet where you enter a formula or function is called the:", "options": ["Status Bar", "Quick Access Toolbar", "Ribbon", "Formula Bar"], "correctAnswer": "Formula Bar" },
    { "id": 20, "questionText": "Which bar is used to display information, and can show the sum, count, and average of cells, etc.?", "options": ["Formula Bar", "Quick Access Toolbar", "Ribbon", "Status Bar"], "correctAnswer": "Status Bar" },
    { "id": 21, "questionText": "What is the main place where work is done in Excel?", "options": ["Formula Bar", "Status Bar", "Ribbon", "Spreadsheet Work Area"], "correctAnswer": "Spreadsheet Work Area" },
    { "id": 22, "questionText": "To resize columns, you can choose a column or a selection of columns, and then click which tab from Home menu?", "options": ["Insert", "Data", "Format", "View"], "correctAnswer": "Format" },
    { "id": 23, "questionText": "To generate charts from data, which tab in the Insert menu should be selected?", "options": ["Data", "Review", "Chart", "View"], "correctAnswer": "Chart" },
    { "id": 24, "questionText": "A chart is data from a worksheet that is represented visually and can be better understood than data that is only seen as numbers. A chart is also commonly known as a:", "options": ["Table", "Formula", "Graph", "Function"], "correctAnswer": "Graph" },
    { "id": 25, "questionText": "What must an Excel formula begin with?", "options": ["+", "-", "*", "="], "correctAnswer": "=" },
    { "id": 26, "questionText": "Which of the following is a built-in function to add numbers in a range?", "options": ["AVERAGE", "MIN", "MAX", "SUM"], "correctAnswer": "SUM" },
    { "id": 27, "questionText": "Which of the following is a built-in function to calculate the average of values in a range?", "options": ["SUM", "MIN", "MAX", "AVERAGE"], "correctAnswer": "AVERAGE" },
    { "id": 28, "questionText": "Which function returns the lowest value discovered in a group of values?", "options": ["SUM", "AVERAGE", "MAX", "MIN"], "correctAnswer": "MIN" },
    { "id": 29, "questionText": "Which function returns the highest value discovered in a group of values?", "options": ["SUM", "AVERAGE", "MIN", "MAX"], "correctAnswer": "MAX" },
    { "id": 30, "questionText": "The IF function is used to test if a certain condition in a worksheet is true or false. What is the IF function?", "options": ["A mathematical function", "A logical function that returns the highest value", "A statistical function", "A logical function used to test a condition"], "correctAnswer": "A logical function used to test a condition" },
    { "id": 31, "questionText": "Which of the following describes 'Formatting' in Excel?", "options": ["Changing the font style of your text", "Changing the size of your text", "Making your text appear in BOLD", "All of the above"], "correctAnswer": "All of the above" },
    { "id": 32, "questionText": "The intersection of row and column in a worksheet is called a:", "options": ["Table", "Spreadsheet", "Workbook", "Cell"], "correctAnswer": "Cell" },
    { "id": 33, "questionText": "A _____ typically contains one or more worksheets.", "options": ["Spreadsheet", "Workbook", "Workspace", "Office"], "correctAnswer": "Workbook" },
    { "id": 34, "questionText": "Data may be represented in different formats like _____ and charts to understand data visually.", "options": ["Cells", "Rows", "Formulas", "Graphs"], "correctAnswer": "Graphs" },
    { "id": 35, "questionText": "Excel's functions are located on the Ribbon's _____ tab.", "options": ["Home", "Data", "Formula", "Function"], "correctAnswer": "Formula" },
    { "id": 36, "questionText": "In a cell, _____ sign and calculations are always used at the beginning of a formula.", "options": ["+", "#", "/", "="], "correctAnswer": "=" },
    { "id": 37, "questionText": "Excel comes with built-in _____ which are predefined formulas.", "options": ["Formulas", "Functions", "Format", "Data"], "correctAnswer": "Functions" },
    { "id": 38, "questionText": "Which of the following allows you to make logical comparisons between a value?", "options": ["For Function", "IF Function", "Else Function", "None"], "correctAnswer": "IF Function" },
    { "id": 39, "questionText": "The IF function is used to test if a certain condition in a worksheet is _____ or false.", "options": ["one", "yes", "zero", "true"], "correctAnswer": "true" },
    { "id": 40, "questionText": "_____ are also commonly known as graphs.", "options": ["Cells", "Charts", "Functions", "Formulas"], "correctAnswer": "Charts" },
    { "id": 41, "questionText": "MS Excel is spreadsheet software.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "True" },
    { "id": 42, "questionText": "You cannot change the background color of a cell.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "False" },
    { "id": 43, "questionText": "Any formula in excel should be preceded by an equal sign.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "True" },
    { "id": 44, "questionText": "An average function of Excel requires reference to the address of cells.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "True" },
    { "id": 45, "questionText": "You cannot merge two cells of an Excel sheet.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "False" },
    { "id": 46, "questionText": "Status Bar is used to display colours.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "False" },
    { "id": 47, "questionText": "The ribbon does not contain the icons (or toolbars) for commands.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "False" },
    { "id": 48, "questionText": "What is the difference between a workbook and worksheet?", "options": ["A worksheet contains one or more workbooks.", "A workbook contains one or more worksheets.", "They are the same.", "A workbook is for text, a worksheet is for numbers."], "correctAnswer": "A workbook contains one or more worksheets." },
    { "id": 49, "questionText": "How can you resize a column in MS Excel?", "options": ["By dragging the column border.", "By selecting the column(s) and using the 'Format' option under the 'Home' tab.", "By right-clicking the column header.", "By using a specific formula."], "correctAnswer": "By selecting the column(s) and using the 'Format' option under the 'Home' tab." },
    { "id": 50, "questionText": "Give examples of any three built-in functions.", "options": ["SUM, AVERAGE, MIN", "ADD, SUBTRACT, MULTIPLY", "TEXT, DATE, TIME", "IF, AND, OR"], "correctAnswer": "SUM, AVERAGE, MIN" }
  ],
  "Google Sheets": [
    { "id": 1, "questionText": "Google Sheets is a widely used spreadsheet program. It is a free online web-based spreadsheet application that is linked with:", "options": ["Microsoft Account", "Apple ID", "Google Account", "Adobe Account"], "correctAnswer": "Google Account" },
    { "id": 2, "questionText": "Which of the following is an advantage of Google Sheets?", "options": ["Offline only", "Limited file formats", "Online editing", "Requires installation"], "correctAnswer": "Online editing" },
    { "id": 3, "questionText": "Google Sheets is developed by:", "options": ["Microsoft Corporation", "Apple Inc.", "Google Corporation", "OpenOffice"], "correctAnswer": "Google Corporation" },
    { "id": 4, "questionText": "Some features of Google Sheets include:", "options": ["Data Grid", "Editing and Formatting", "Exploring", "All of the above"], "correctAnswer": "All of the above" },
    { "id": 5, "questionText": "Which feature of Google Sheets allows it to save and process data in columns and rows and allows you to do calculations?", "options": ["Editing and Formatting", "Exploring", "Data Grid", "Many File Formats"], "correctAnswer": "Data Grid" },
    { "id": 6, "questionText": "Real-time shared editing and formatting of spreadsheets is possible with:", "options": ["Microsoft Excel", "OpenOffice Calc", "Google Sheets", "LibreOffice Calc"], "correctAnswer": "Google Sheets" },
    { "id": 7, "questionText": "What does the 'Exploring' feature in Google Sheets allow users to do?", "options": ["Change font styles", "Ask questions, make charts, visualize data, create pivot tables", "Insert images", "Save files"], "correctAnswer": "Ask questions, make charts, visualize data, create pivot tables" },
    { "id": 8, "questionText": "Google Sheets supports multiple spreadsheet file types and formats. This feature is known as:", "options": ["Online Editing", "Data Grid", "Many File Formats", "Exploring"], "correctAnswer": "Many File Formats" },
    { "id": 9, "questionText": "Enabling the Chrome extension makes offline editing possible in:", "options": ["Microsoft Excel", "LibreOffice Calc", "Google Sheets", "OpenOffice"], "correctAnswer": "Google Sheets" },
    { "id": 10, "questionText": "Google Sheets allows users to create new worksheets, with each new worksheet having a default name of:", "options": ["Sheet A", "Sheet 1", "New Sheet", "Workbook 1"], "correctAnswer": "Sheet 1" },
    { "id": 11, "questionText": "To rename a Google Sheet, you click on \"Untitled spreadsheet\" and type in the new name. Where is this option usually found?", "options": ["Menu bar", "Toolbar", "Title bar", "Formula bar"], "correctAnswer": "Title bar" },
    { "id": 12, "questionText": "The menu bar in Google Sheets contains different menus like:", "options": ["File", "Edit", "View", "All of the above"], "correctAnswer": "All of the above" },
    { "id": 13, "questionText": "The most common actions from the menu are on the:", "options": ["Menu bar", "Toolbar", "Formula bar", "Status bar"], "correctAnswer": "Toolbar" },
    { "id": 14, "questionText": "The Toolbar's Groups are collections of related commands. The commands can be divided into:", "options": ["Tabs", "Categories", "Dividers", "Functions"], "correctAnswer": "Categories" },
    { "id": 15, "questionText": "The buttons you press to perform actions are known as:", "options": ["Functions", "Formulas", "Commands", "Icons"], "correctAnswer": "Commands" },
    { "id": 16, "questionText": "Each sheet in the spreadsheet is composed of columns and rows just like a table. Each column in a sheet is identified by a letter starting with:", "options": ["1", "A", "a", "I"], "correctAnswer": "A" },
    { "id": 17, "questionText": "Columns Headers are identified by a number, starting with:", "options": ["1", "A", "0", "I"], "correctAnswer": "A" },
    { "id": 18, "questionText": "The intersection of a row and column is called a:", "options": ["Row", "Column", "Sheet", "Cell"], "correctAnswer": "Cell" },
    { "id": 19, "questionText": "What does the Name Box display?", "options": ["The sheet name", "The formula", "The reference of which cell or range you have selected", "The current date"], "correctAnswer": "The reference of which cell or range you have selected" },
    { "id": 20, "questionText": "Which of the following describes selecting a Column?", "options": ["Columns are selected by left-clicking on Column Headers", "To select column A, click on the letter A in the column bar", "Both a and b", "Columns are selected by right-clicking on Column Headers"], "correctAnswer": "Both a and b" },
    { "id": 21, "questionText": "To select row 1, click on the number 1 in the row bar. Which of the following describes selecting a Row?", "options": ["Rows are selected by left-clicking on Column Headers", "Rows are selected by left-clicking on Row Headers", "Rows are selected by right-clicking on Row Headers", "Rows are selected by dragging the row"], "correctAnswer": "Rows are selected by left-clicking on Row Headers" },
    { "id": 22, "questionText": "The all-inclusive spreadsheet can be carefully chosen by clicking on the rectangle in the top-left corner of the spreadsheet. This describes selecting the:", "options": ["Active Cell", "Entire Row", "Entire Column", "Entire Sheet"], "correctAnswer": "Entire Sheet" },
    { "id": 23, "questionText": "What must a formula in Google Sheets always start with?", "options": ["+", "-", "*", "="], "correctAnswer": "=" },
    { "id": 24, "questionText": "Google Sheets has many predefined formulas called:", "options": ["Functions", "Formulas", "Expressions", "Commands"], "correctAnswer": "Functions" },
    { "id": 25, "questionText": "Which function calculates the average (arithmetic mean) of numbers in a range?", "options": ["SUM", "COUNT", "MAX", "AVERAGE"], "correctAnswer": "AVERAGE" },
    { "id": 26, "questionText": "Which function counts cells with numbers in a range?", "options": ["SUM", "COUNT", "MAX", "MIN"], "correctAnswer": "COUNT" },
    { "id": 27, "questionText": "Which function returns the highest value in a range?", "options": ["SUM", "COUNT", "MAX", "MIN"], "correctAnswer": "MAX" },
    { "id": 28, "questionText": "Which function returns the lowest value in a range?", "options": ["SUM", "COUNT", "MAX", "MIN"], "correctAnswer": "MIN" },
    { "id": 29, "questionText": "Which function adds together numbers in a range?", "options": ["AVERAGE", "COUNT", "MAX", "SUM"], "correctAnswer": "SUM" },
    { "id": 30, "questionText": "Which company developed Microsoft Excel?", "options": ["Microsoft Corporation", "Google LLC", "OpenOffice", "LibreOffice"], "correctAnswer": "Microsoft Corporation" },
    { "id": 31, "questionText": "Google Sheets was launched as a pack of G Suite in which year?", "options": ["2000", "2002", "2006", "2004"], "correctAnswer": "2006" },
    { "id": 32, "questionText": "Excel was launched as part of MS Office in which year?", "options": ["1987", "1990", "1995", "2000"], "correctAnswer": "1990" },
    { "id": 33, "questionText": "Google Sheets allows offline use. Which of the following is true?", "options": ["It does not support offline mode.", "It supports offline mode only with a premium subscription.", "It allows both online and offline use.", "It only supports offline use."], "correctAnswer": "It allows both online and offline use." },
    { "id": 34, "questionText": "How many languages is Google Sheets available in?", "options": ["50 languages", "65 languages", "83 languages", "91 languages"], "correctAnswer": "83 languages" },
    { "id": 35, "questionText": "How many languages is Excel available in?", "options": ["50 languages", "65 languages", "83 languages", "91 languages"], "correctAnswer": "91 languages" },
    { "id": 36, "questionText": "Google Sheets uses Google Drive for storage. Which of the following is true?", "options": ["It uses OneDrive.", "It uses Dropbox.", "It uses Google Drive.", "It uses iCloud."], "correctAnswer": "It uses Google Drive." },
    { "id": 37, "questionText": "For small volumes of data, which spreadsheet program is generally better?", "options": ["Excel", "Google Sheets", "Both are equal", "Neither is good"], "correctAnswer": "Google Sheets" },
    { "id": 38, "questionText": "Google Sheets is a free online web-based spreadsheet application that is linked with Google Account.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "True" },
    { "id": 39, "questionText": "Google Sheets is a spreadsheet program developed by Google Corporation.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "True" },
    { "id": 40, "questionText": "Google Sheets does not require downloading and installation of the program. It simply runs on your browser.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "True" },
    { "id": 41, "questionText": "A formula in Google Sheets is used to do mathematical calculations.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "True" },
    { "id": 42, "questionText": "Formulas always start with an equal sign (=) typed in the cell, followed by your calculation.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "True" },
    { "id": 43, "questionText": "Google Sheets has many predefined formulas called functions.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "True" },
    { "id": 44, "questionText": "Functions are typed with '=' and the 'function's name'.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "True" },
    { "id": 45, "questionText": "Students will be learning databases like MS Access.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "False" },
    { "id": 46, "questionText": "What is Google Sheets?", "options": ["A word processor", "A presentation tool", "A free online web-based spreadsheet application", "A database management system"], "correctAnswer": "A free online web-based spreadsheet application" },
    { "id": 47, "questionText": "Why do we use Google Sheets?", "options": ["For offline work only", "For complex data analysis", "For real-time collaboration and easy sharing", "To create professional reports"], "correctAnswer": "For real-time collaboration and easy sharing" },
    { "id": 48, "questionText": "What are the applications of Google Sheets?", "options": ["Data storage", "Project management", "Programming", "All of the above"], "correctAnswer": "All of the above" },
    { "id": 49, "questionText": "How to create new sheets in Google Sheets?", "options": ["By clicking the 'Save' button.", "By going to 'File' -> 'New Workbook'.", "By clicking the '+' button on the sheet tab bar or using shortcut Shift + F11.", "By selecting 'Insert' -> 'New Sheet'."], "correctAnswer": "By clicking the '+' button on the sheet tab bar or using shortcut Shift + F11." },
    { "id": 50, "questionText": "What are the formulas in Google Sheets?", "options": ["Predefined functions", "Mathematical expressions that start with an equal sign", "Text strings", "Graphics"], "correctAnswer": "Mathematical expressions that start with an equal sign" }
  ],
  "Computational Thinking": [
    { "id": 1, "questionText": "Computational thinking is a set of problem-solving processes that includes several characteristics and perspectives. Which of the following defines computational thinking?", "options": ["The ability to program a computer.", "The ability to use complex software.", "A problem-solving approach.", "The ability to create algorithms only."], "correctAnswer": "A problem-solving approach." },
    { "id": 2, "questionText": "The fundamental steps of computational thinking are:", "options": ["Problem Solving, Coding, Debugging, Testing", "Design, Develop, Deploy, Document", "Decomposition, Pattern Recognition, Abstraction, Algorithm Design", "Analyze, Create, Evaluate, Optimize"], "correctAnswer": "Decomposition, Pattern Recognition, Abstraction, Algorithm Design" },
    { "id": 3, "questionText": "Breaking down a complex problem into smaller, more manageable parts is called:", "options": ["Abstraction", "Pattern Recognition", "Algorithm Design", "Decomposition"], "correctAnswer": "Decomposition" },
    { "id": 4, "questionText": "Observing patterns, trends, and regularities in data along with looking for similarities among and within problems is known as:", "options": ["Decomposition", "Abstraction", "Algorithm Design", "Pattern Recognition"], "correctAnswer": "Pattern Recognition" },
    { "id": 5, "questionText": "Focusing only on the important details, while ignoring irrelevant information, is called:", "options": ["Decomposition", "Pattern Recognition", "Algorithm Design", "Abstraction"], "correctAnswer": "Abstraction" },
    { "id": 6, "questionText": "Developing a step-by-step approach for solving a problem and similar problems is called:", "options": ["Decomposition", "Pattern Recognition", "Abstraction", "Algorithm Design"], "correctAnswer": "Algorithm Design" },
    { "id": 7, "questionText": "A finite sequence of activities to be processed for getting a task done or the desired output from a given input is called an:", "options": ["Program", "Flowchart", "Pseudocode", "Algorithm"], "correctAnswer": "Algorithm" },
    { "id": 8, "questionText": "In an algorithm, what is the first step?", "options": ["Input", "Process", "Output", "Start"], "correctAnswer": "Start" },
    { "id": 9, "questionText": "A graphical representation of an algorithm is called a:", "options": ["Pseudocode", "Algorithm", "Program", "Flowchart"], "correctAnswer": "Flowchart" },
    { "id": 10, "questionText": "In a flowchart, what symbol represents the beginning and the end of a flowchart?", "options": ["Rectangle", "Parallelogram", "Diamond", "Oval / Start/Stop box"], "correctAnswer": "Oval / Start/Stop box" },
    { "id": 11, "questionText": "In a flowchart, what symbol represents input and output instructions?", "options": ["Oval", "Rectangle", "Diamond", "Parallelogram / I/O box"], "correctAnswer": "Parallelogram / I/O box" },
    { "id": 12, "questionText": "In a flowchart, what symbol represents processing instructions?", "options": ["Oval", "Rectangle / Process box", "Diamond", "Parallelogram"], "correctAnswer": "Rectangle / Process box" },
    { "id": 13, "questionText": "In a flowchart, what symbol represents decision with two options—'Yes' and 'No'?", "options": ["Oval", "Rectangle", "Parallelogram", "Diamond / Decision box"], "correctAnswer": "Diamond / Decision box" },
    { "id": 14, "questionText": "In a flowchart, what symbol shows the direction of flow of data and instructions?", "options": ["Oval", "Rectangle", "Diamond", "Lines with Arrowhead / Flow lines"], "correctAnswer": "Lines with Arrowhead / Flow lines" },
    { "id": 15, "questionText": "What is the purpose of the 'Connector' symbol (Circle) in a flowchart?", "options": ["Represents a decision", "Represents input/output", "Used to connect various sections of a flowchart", "Represents a process"], "correctAnswer": "Used to connect various sections of a flowchart" },
    { "id": 16, "questionText": "Which of the following is a rule for drawing a flowchart?", "options": ["There can be only one start and one stop symbol", "Only one flow line can be used with the Start symbol", "Only one flow line can come out from a process symbol", "All of the above"], "correctAnswer": "All of the above" },
    { "id": 17, "questionText": "Flowcharts are simple, making changes to them a problem.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "False" },
    { "id": 18, "questionText": "The abbreviation 5%Z=1 is used to show:", "options": ["Remainder in a division process is 1.", "5 percent value is 1.", "The remainder in a division process is 1.", "5 percent of Z is 1."], "correctAnswer": "The remainder in a division process is 1." },
    { "id": 19, "questionText": "Computational thinking helps the programmer to work out exactly what to instruct the computer to do. The solution can be converted into the:", "options": ["Algorithm", "Flowchart", "Pseudocode", "Programming language"], "correctAnswer": "Programming language" },
    { "id": 20, "questionText": "Which of the following is an advantage of thinking abstractly?", "options": ["Caching can speed up a process.", "Concurrency speeds up the solution.", "Allows us to make predictions.", "Can be done with flowcharts."], "correctAnswer": "Allows us to make predictions." },
    { "id": 21, "questionText": "What is a disadvantage of thinking abstractly?", "options": ["Caching can be complicated.", "It may not be entirely possible with an event-driven approach.", "Too many factors that are changeable may mean the scenario is too complex to model accurately.", "It may be difficult to program."], "correctAnswer": "Too many factors that are changeable may mean the scenario is too complex to model accurately." },
    { "id": 22, "questionText": "What is an advantage of 'Thinking ahead' in computational thinking?", "options": ["Allows us to make predictions.", "Can be done with flowcharts.", "Caching can speed up a process.", "Concurrency speeds up the solution."], "correctAnswer": "Caching can speed up a process." },
    { "id": 23, "questionText": "What is a disadvantage of 'Thinking ahead'?", "options": ["Too complex to model accurately.", "Caching can be complicated to implement. Caching requires the correct data to be fetched for the next task.", "Not entirely possible with an event-driven approach.", "Difficult to program."], "correctAnswer": "Caching can be complicated to implement. Caching requires the correct data to be fetched for the next task." },
    { "id": 24, "questionText": "'Thinking procedurally' or 'Decomposition' can be done with:", "options": ["Algorithms", "Flowcharts", "Pseudocode", "Programming"], "correctAnswer": "Flowcharts" },
    { "id": 25, "questionText": "What is an advantage of 'Thinking concurrently'?", "options": ["Allows us to make predictions.", "Can be done with flowcharts.", "Concurrency speeds up the solution.", "Less difficult to program."], "correctAnswer": "Concurrency speeds up the solution." },
    { "id": 26, "questionText": "What is a disadvantage of 'Thinking concurrently'?", "options": ["Too complex to model accurately.", "Caching can be complicated.", "Not entirely possible with an event-driven approach.", "It may be difficult to program."], "correctAnswer": "It may be difficult to program." },
    { "id": 27, "questionText": "A collection of instructions to solve a problem simply described in plain English is called:", "options": ["Algorithm", "Flowchart", "Program", "Pseudocode"], "correctAnswer": "Pseudocode" },
    { "id": 28, "questionText": "Which of the following is NOT a basic rule for writing pseudocode?", "options": ["Put the tasks in the proper order.", "Use the proper sentence case for each type of word.", "Apply the proper naming conventions.", "Must be written in a specific programming language."], "correctAnswer": "Must be written in a specific programming language." },
    { "id": 29, "questionText": "What is the goal of 'Conditions in problem solving'?", "options": ["To complicate the problem.", "To make decisions based on assumptions.", "To tell us the right path based on some tests.", "To generate random outcomes."], "correctAnswer": "To tell us the right path based on some tests." },
    { "id": 30, "questionText": "Which of the following describes an 'if condition'?", "options": ["Only if a block of statements is executed.", "If the condition is true, nothing happens.", "If the condition is true, a statement or a block of statements are only executed.", "If the condition is false, a statement is executed."], "correctAnswer": "If the condition is true, a statement or a block of statements are only executed." },
    { "id": 31, "questionText": "Which of the following describes an 'if then else' condition?", "options": ["If the condition is true, only 'then' statements are executed.", "If the condition is false, only 'else' statements are executed.", "If a specific condition is true, execute 'then' block; otherwise, execute 'else' block.", "Executes both 'then' and 'else' blocks regardless of condition."], "correctAnswer": "If a specific condition is true, execute 'then' block; otherwise, execute 'else' block." },
    { "id": 32, "questionText": "What is 'Iteration' in problem solving?", "options": ["A single step in problem solving.", "A way to make decisions.", "Repeating an action or a set of actions until a particular condition is satisfied.", "Breaking down a problem."], "correctAnswer": "Repeating an action or a set of actions until a particular condition is satisfied." },
    { "id": 33, "questionText": "A loop in programming can execute statements several times depending on a condition. What is a block whose label begins with 'forever' or 'repeat' called?", "options": ["Conditional construct", "Iterative construct", "Looping construct", "Sequential construct"], "correctAnswer": "Looping construct" },
    { "id": 34, "questionText": "The placement of one object within another object, in problem solving, different elements may be placed within other elements. This describes:", "options": ["Looping", "Iteration", "Abstraction", "Nesting"], "correctAnswer": "Nesting" },
    { "id": 35, "questionText": "When conditions are placed within other conditions to solve a problem, these conditions will have many 'if' condition blocks that are checked line by line until a condition is true. This describes:", "options": ["Simple Conditions", "Iterative Conditions", "Nested Conditions", "Sequential Conditions"], "correctAnswer": "Nested Conditions" },
    { "id": 36, "questionText": "Developing a step-by-step approach for solving a problem is:", "options": ["Decomposition", "Abstraction", "Algorithm Design", "Pattern Recognition"], "correctAnswer": "Algorithm Design" },
    { "id": 37, "questionText": "_____ allows us to take a complex problem, understand what the problem is and develop possible solutions.", "options": ["Computational thinking", "Excel", "Formulas", "None of these"], "correctAnswer": "Computational thinking" },
    { "id": 38, "questionText": "Observing patterns, trends, and regularities in data along with looking for similarities among and within the problem are:", "options": ["Decomposition", "Abstraction", "Algorithm Design", "Pattern Recognition"], "correctAnswer": "Pattern Recognition" },
    { "id": 39, "questionText": "Focusing only on the important details, while ignoring irrelevant information is:", "options": ["Decomposition", "Abstraction", "Algorithm Design", "Pattern Recognition"], "correctAnswer": "Abstraction" },
    { "id": 40, "questionText": "Sometimes we want to repeat an action again and again, which is called:", "options": ["Iteration", "Solution", "Copying", "Deletion"], "correctAnswer": "Iteration" },
    { "id": 41, "questionText": "There can be only one start and _____ stop symbol in a flowchart.", "options": ["One", "Two", "Three", "Four"], "correctAnswer": "One" },
    { "id": 42, "questionText": "The Start/Stop box is represented by:", "options": ["An oval", "A parallelogram", "A rectangle", "A diamond"], "correctAnswer": "An oval" },
    { "id": 43, "questionText": "The decision box is represented by:", "options": ["An oval", "A parallelogram", "A rectangle", "A diamond"], "correctAnswer": "A diamond" },
    { "id": 44, "questionText": "What is the full form of CT?", "options": ["Computer Technology", "Computational Thinking", "Computer Tomography", "None of these"], "correctAnswer": "Computational Thinking" },
    { "id": 45, "questionText": "_____ is the placement of one object within another object.", "options": ["Halting", "Flowchart", "Nesting", "None of these"], "correctAnswer": "Nesting" },
    { "id": 46, "questionText": "An algorithm always begins with the word Start.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "True" },
    { "id": 47, "questionText": "A diamond shows the direction of the flow of data and instructions in a flowchart.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "False" },
    { "id": 48, "questionText": "Computational thinking does not allow the development of solutions to a problem.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "False" },
    { "id": 49, "questionText": "Each step in an algorithm should be written in a separate line.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "True" },
    { "id": 50, "questionText": "The flow lines can cross each other.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "False" }
  ],
  "Programming": [
    { "id": 1, "questionText": "Programming is the art of writing instructions to tell a computer what to do. A set of instructions is called a:", "options": ["Algorithm", "Flowchart", "Program", "Pseudocode"], "correctAnswer": "Program" },
    { "id": 2, "questionText": "What is a programming language that is perfect for making games, animations, interactive stories, and other visually rich programs?", "options": ["Python", "Java", "Scratch", "C++"], "correctAnswer": "Scratch" },
    { "id": 3, "questionText": "Scratch is created by the MIT Media Lab and has been translated into more than how many different languages?", "options": ["50", "60", "70", "80"], "correctAnswer": "70" },
    { "id": 4, "questionText": "In Scratch, characters or objects that perform actions are called:", "options": ["Blocks", "Stages", "Sprites", "Scripts"], "correctAnswer": "Sprites" },
    { "id": 5, "questionText": "Which category of Scratch blocks is used for moving sprites around the stage?", "options": ["Looks", "Sound", "Motion", "Events"], "correctAnswer": "Motion" },
    { "id": 6, "questionText": "Which category of Scratch blocks is used for animating sprites, giving them speech bubbles, and changing their size and appearance?", "options": ["Motion", "Looks", "Sound", "Control"], "correctAnswer": "Looks" },
    { "id": 7, "questionText": "Which category of Scratch blocks is used to regulate sound functions and playing recordings or musical notes?", "options": ["Motion", "Looks", "Sound", "Events"], "correctAnswer": "Sound" },
    { "id": 8, "questionText": "Which category of Scratch blocks is used to make the sprite perform according to the event done (e.g., when the green flag is clicked)?", "options": ["Motion", "Looks", "Sound", "Events"], "correctAnswer": "Events" },
    { "id": 9, "questionText": "Which category of Scratch blocks is used to describe what will happen, when, and for making bits of your program repeat, forever, etc.?", "options": ["Motion", "Events", "Sensing", "Control"], "correctAnswer": "Control" },
    { "id": 10, "questionText": "Which category of Scratch blocks is used to test whether your sprite is touching another sprite or another color, or to get information about other sprites?", "options": ["Control", "Operators", "Sensing", "Variables"], "correctAnswer": "Sensing" },
    { "id": 11, "questionText": "Which category of Scratch blocks is used for Maths equations, random numbers, and handling strings?", "options": ["Sensing", "Variables", "Operators", "My Blocks"], "correctAnswer": "Operators" },
    { "id": 12, "questionText": "Which category of Scratch blocks is used to change the values recorded in Scratch, storing a value?", "options": ["Operators", "My Blocks", "Variables", "Sensing"], "correctAnswer": "Variables" },
    { "id": 13, "questionText": "Which category of Scratch blocks is used to make a new block from Scratch, containing procedures for the sprite that is selected at the moment?", "options": ["Operators", "Variables", "My Blocks", "Events"], "correctAnswer": "My Blocks" },
    { "id": 14, "questionText": "What is a variable in programming?", "options": ["A fixed value", "A block of code", "A place for some value in memory, much like x and y are popular variables in algebra.", "A function"], "correctAnswer": "A place for some value in memory, much like x and y are popular variables in algebra." },
    { "id": 15, "questionText": "What is a Boolean expression in programming?", "options": ["An expression that can only be true.", "An expression that can only be false.", "An expression that is either true or false.", "An expression that returns a number."], "correctAnswer": "An expression that is either true or false." },
    { "id": 16, "questionText": "Which of the following is an example of a Boolean expression in Scratch?", "options": ["> 50", "+ 50", "- 50", "* 50"], "correctAnswer": "> 50" },
    { "id": 17, "questionText": "Conditional statements allow your program to make decisions. They are also known as:", "options": ["Loops", "Variables", "If-then statements", "Functions"], "correctAnswer": "If-then statements" },
    { "id": 18, "questionText": "Which of the following is NOT an example of a conditional statement?", "options": ["If", "If-then-else", "Forever", "If-else"], "correctAnswer": "Forever" },
    { "id": 19, "questionText": "What does an 'if-else' construct allow?", "options": ["To execute only one block of code.", "To execute both blocks of code.", "To execute one block of code if a condition is true, and another if it's false.", "To loop indefinitely."], "correctAnswer": "To execute one block of code if a condition is true, and another if it's false." },
    { "id": 20, "questionText": "When a program needs to repeat a block of code continuously, which loop is used?", "options": ["Repeat loop", "Until loop", "Forever loop", "For loop"], "correctAnswer": "Forever loop" },
    { "id": 21, "questionText": "A loop that has been inserted inside another main loop is called a:", "options": ["Simple loop", "Single loop", "Nested loop", "Complex loop"], "correctAnswer": "Nested loop" },
    { "id": 22, "questionText": "In programming, a function is a block of code that you may reuse repeatedly rather than having to write it out several times. What is a function?", "options": ["A variable", "A loop", "A block of code to perform a specific task", "A conditional statement"], "correctAnswer": "A block of code to perform a specific task" },
    { "id": 23, "questionText": "What is 'Cloning' in Scratch?", "options": ["Copying a sprite.", "Duplicating the entire project.", "A sprite can duplicate itself while the project is active.", "Renaming a sprite."], "correctAnswer": "A sprite can duplicate itself while the project is active." },
    { "id": 24, "questionText": "In the Pong game example, how many paddles are created for two players?", "options": ["1", "2", "3", "4"], "correctAnswer": "2" },
    { "id": 25, "questionText": "In the Pong game example, how many goals are created?", "options": ["1", "2", "3", "4"], "correctAnswer": "2" },
    { "id": 26, "questionText": "To add a new sprite in Scratch, you can click on:", "options": ["The 'Save' button.", "The 'File' menu.", "The 'Paint' button or 'Choose a Sprite' icon.", "The 'Events' block."], "correctAnswer": "The 'Paint' button or 'Choose a Sprite' icon." },
    { "id": 27, "questionText": "What is the purpose of renaming sprites in Scratch?", "options": ["To change their color.", "To make them larger.", "To give them meaningful names for easier management.", "To make them invisible."], "correctAnswer": "To give them meaningful names for easier management." },
    { "id": 28, "questionText": "In the Pong game, where does the ball initially move when the green flag is clicked?", "options": ["(100, 100)", "(-100, -100)", "(0, 0)", "Random position"], "correctAnswer": "(0, 0)" },
    { "id": 29, "questionText": "To control the ball's movement and make it bounce off walls and paddles, which category of blocks would be primarily used?", "options": ["Looks", "Sound", "Motion and Control", "Events"], "correctAnswer": "Motion and Control" },
    { "id": 30, "questionText": "To detect if the ball touches a paddle or a wall, which category of blocks is used?", "options": ["Motion", "Control", "Sensing", "Operators"], "correctAnswer": "Sensing" },
    { "id": 31, "questionText": "What is used to store the scores of player 1 and player 2 in the Pong game?", "options": ["Lists", "Arrays", "Variables", "Constants"], "correctAnswer": "Variables" },
    { "id": 32, "questionText": "To create a new variable in Scratch, you click on \"Make a Variable\" and type the new variable name in the new variable name box. Which of the following is a valid variable name?", "options": ["Player 1 Score", "Player_1_Score", "Player1Score", "Player-1-Score"], "correctAnswer": "Player1Score" },
    { "id": 33, "questionText": "In the Pong game, when the ball touches the goal, what happens to the player's score?", "options": ["It remains unchanged.", "It decreases by 1.", "It increases by 1.", "It resets to 0."], "correctAnswer": "It increases by 1." },
    { "id": 34, "questionText": "To end the game when a player reaches a specific score (e.g., 5), which block would be used?", "options": ["Repeat loop", "Forever loop", "Stop all", "If-then-else"], "correctAnswer": "Stop all" },
    { "id": 35, "questionText": "To add a background to the Scratch project, you click on \"Choose a backdrop\". What are the options available?", "options": ["Fantasy, Music, Sports", "Outdoors, Space, Underwater", "Patterns", "All of the above"], "correctAnswer": "All of the above" },
    { "id": 36, "questionText": "After the game is over, what text is added to the backdrop?", "options": ["You Win!", "Game Start", "Game Over", "Play Again"], "correctAnswer": "Game Over" },
    { "id": 37, "questionText": "Programming is the art of writing instructions to tell a computer what to do.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "True" },
    { "id": 38, "questionText": "A set of instructions is called a Program.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "True" },
    { "id": 39, "questionText": "Scratch is a programming language that is perfect for making games, animations, interactive stories, and other visually rich programs.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "True" },
    { "id": 40, "questionText": "Sprites can be moved, drawn on the screen, respond to clicks, change their appearance, and interact with each other.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "True" },
    { "id": 41, "questionText": "The blocks of Scratch are sorted into the following categories: Motion, Looks, Sound, Events, Control, Sensing, Operators, Variables, and My Blocks.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "True" },
    { "id": 42, "questionText": "In Scratch, variables are represented with blocks shaped like elongated circles, uniquely labelled by you.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "True" },
    { "id": 43, "questionText": "A Boolean expression is an expression that is either true or false.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "True" },
    { "id": 44, "questionText": "A condition is something that must be true for something to happen.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "True" },
    { "id": 45, "questionText": "A loop in programming can execute statements several times depending on a condition. In Scratch, any block whose label begins with 'forever' or 'repeat' is a looping construct.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "True" },
    { "id": 46, "questionText": "In programming, a variable is a place for some value in memory, much like x and y are popular variables in algebra.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "True" },
    { "id": 47, "questionText": "Which of the following items are in each Scratch project?", "options": ["Sprites", "Stage", "Scripts", "All of these"], "correctAnswer": "All of these" },
    { "id": 48, "questionText": "A loop and a _____ are combined in the \"repeat until\" block.", "options": ["Sprite", "Stage", "Variable", "Condition"], "correctAnswer": "Condition" },
    { "id": 49, "questionText": "Which of the following is used to make a new block from Scratch?", "options": ["Sensing", "Control", "My Blocks", "Variables"], "correctAnswer": "My Blocks" },
    { "id": 50, "questionText": "In programming, a function is a block of code that you may _____ repeatedly rather than having to write it out several times.", "options": ["Reuse", "Print", "Destroy", "All of these"], "correctAnswer": "Reuse" }
  ],
  "Digital Citizenship": [
    { "id": 1, "questionText": "Digital citizenship involves being safe, responsible, and respectful online. What is the importance of digital citizenship?", "options": ["To avoid using technology.", "To become a master programmer.", "To be safe, responsible, and respectful online.", "To learn new technologies."], "correctAnswer": "To be safe, responsible, and respectful online." },
    { "id": 2, "questionText": "The Internet is also called the 'NET' or 'Network of Networks', which means:", "options": ["Local Network", "Wide Area Network", "International Network", "Private Network"], "correctAnswer": "International Network" },
    { "id": 3, "questionText": "Which of the following is an advantage of the Internet?", "options": ["Information overload", "Cybercrime", "Treasure of Information", "Digital divide"], "correctAnswer": "Treasure of Information" },
    { "id": 4, "questionText": "The Internet provides many useful services like chatting, email, video conferencing, etc., which help people to:", "options": ["Waste time", "Create malware", "Connect all around the world", "Isolate themselves"], "correctAnswer": "Connect all around the world" },
    { "id": 5, "questionText": "Which Internet service allows students to study from home in their comfortable timings?", "options": ["Promoting Business", "Web Services", "Entertainment", "E-Learning"], "correctAnswer": "E-Learning" },
    { "id": 6, "questionText": "For entertainment, people can listen to music, watch movies, and play games on the Internet. Which of the following is an advantage of the Internet?", "options": ["Cyberbullying", "Plagiarism", "Entertainment", "Virus"], "correctAnswer": "Entertainment" },
    { "id": 7, "questionText": "What is the term for banking systems that have taken the banking system to a high level, allowing mobile payments and bills to be paid from mobile phones?", "options": ["Online Banking", "Internet Banking", "Digital Banking", "Mobile Banking"], "correctAnswer": "Online Banking" },
    { "id": 8, "questionText": "Digital media bias refers to the idea that the media is reporting the news in a biased or partial way. What is digital media bias?", "options": ["Objective reporting", "Fair presentation of facts", "Reporting news in a biased or partial way", "Reporting only positive news"], "correctAnswer": "Reporting news in a biased or partial way" },
    { "id": 9, "questionText": "Ethics is a system of moral principles. They affect how people make decisions and lead their lives. What is ethics?", "options": ["Legal guidelines", "Social norms", "A system of moral principles", "Economic rules"], "correctAnswer": "A system of moral principles" },
    { "id": 10, "questionText": "The digital environment is an increasingly popular tool in family and child research that is argued to pose new ethical challenges. There are many issues in digital environments, such as:", "options": ["Online privacy", "Digital footprint", "Participant privacy", "All of the above"], "correctAnswer": "All of the above" },
    { "id": 11, "questionText": "Cyber crimes are offenses that are committed using computers and smart devices connected to the Internet. Which of the following is a type of cybercrime?", "options": ["Malware", "Ransomware", "E-mail Spoofing", "Phishing"], "correctAnswer": "Phishing" },
    { "id": 12, "questionText": "When someone sends e-mails that appear genuine from a trusted e-mail ID but, in reality, they are not to be trusted, it's called:", "options": ["Spam", "Phishing", "E-mail Spoofing", "Hacking"], "correctAnswer": "E-mail Spoofing" },
    { "id": 13, "questionText": "Which type of cybercrime involves attempting to acquire sensitive information such as usernames, passwords, and credit card details by masquerading as a trustworthy entity in an electronic communication?", "options": ["Spamming", "E-mail Spoofing", "Hacking", "Phishing"], "correctAnswer": "Phishing" },
    { "id": 14, "questionText": "Phishing is also called:", "options": ["Spamming", "Malware", "Data fishing", "Encryption"], "correctAnswer": "Data fishing" },
    { "id": 15, "questionText": "It refers to the spamming of bulk mail to an unidentified source. Which of the following describes Spamming?", "options": ["Sending personal emails", "Sending encrypted messages", "Sending bulk-advertising mail to many accounts", "Sending a single suspicious email"], "correctAnswer": "Sending bulk-advertising mail to many accounts" },
    { "id": 16, "questionText": "Which of the following is a measure to avoid spam?", "options": ["Reply to all emails", "Open all attachments", "Preview your message before opening them", "Click on suspicious links"], "correctAnswer": "Preview your message before opening them" },
    { "id": 17, "questionText": "What is 'E-mail account Hacking'?", "options": ["Sending legitimate emails.", "Securing your email account.", "Another common method used by cybercriminals to trouble victims, involving malware or other tricks to obtain their email ID and password.", "Creating a new email account."], "correctAnswer": "Another common method used by cybercriminals to trouble victims, involving malware or other tricks to obtain their email ID and password." },
    { "id": 18, "questionText": "Which of the following is a measure to avoid hacking?", "options": ["Keep a password for your Wi-fi connection and computer.", "Keep changing your passwords.", "Keep updating your operating system.", "All of the above"], "correctAnswer": "All of the above" },
    { "id": 19, "questionText": "What is a 'Cyber Troll'?", "options": ["A helpful online user.", "A person who promotes positive online interactions.", "A person who purposely posts opposing, sarcastic, demeaning, or insulting comments about something or someone.", "A person who creates online content."], "correctAnswer": "A person who purposely posts opposing, sarcastic, demeaning, or insulting comments about something or someone." },
    { "id": 20, "questionText": "Social engineering is a technique used by cybercriminals to gain the information from individuals. What is 'Social Engineering'?", "options": ["A software development method.", "A networking protocol.", "A technique used by cybercriminals to gain information from individuals.", "A form of marketing."], "correctAnswer": "A technique used by cybercriminals to gain information from individuals." },
    { "id": 21, "questionText": "Which of the following describes 'Cyber Bullying'?", "options": ["A type of online game.", "The use of the Internet, e-mail, instant messaging, chat rooms, or social networks, such as Facebook, Twitter, etc. to harass, demean, embarrass or intimidate someone else.", "A new programming language.", "A secure online communication method."], "correctAnswer": "The use of the Internet, e-mail, instant messaging, chat rooms, or social networks, such as Facebook, Twitter, etc. to harass, demean, embarrass or intimidate someone else." },
    { "id": 22, "questionText": "Which of the following is a measure to prevent Cyber Bullying?", "options": ["Never remember to share personal details such as age, address, date of birth, etc. with unknown people on social media.", "Restrict access to your data on social media platforms.", "Try avoiding friend requests from unknown people on social media.", "All of the above"], "correctAnswer": "All of the above" },
    { "id": 23, "questionText": "What is 'Online Transaction Fraud'?", "options": ["A secure way to shop online.", "Online transaction fraud refers to the illegal withdrawal or transfer of money from one bank account to another by a cybercriminal.", "A method for safe online payments.", "A tool for verifying online transactions."], "correctAnswer": "Online transaction fraud refers to the illegal withdrawal or transfer of money from one bank account to another by a cybercriminal." },
    { "id": 24, "questionText": "Which type of online transaction fraud involves cybercriminals appearing to be from a bank or credit card service provider to steal identity?", "options": ["Job Frauds", "Banking Frauds", "Identity Theft", "Online Shopping Frauds"], "correctAnswer": "Identity Theft" },
    { "id": 25, "questionText": "Which type of online transaction fraud involves cybercriminals portraying incorrect details as an employer?", "options": ["Identity Theft", "Banking Frauds", "Job Frauds", "Online Shopping Frauds"], "correctAnswer": "Job Frauds" },
    { "id": 26, "questionText": "Which type of online transaction fraud involves cybercriminals fraudulently obtaining money from users for investment by posing as a bank or other financial institution?", "options": ["Identity Theft", "Banking Frauds", "Job Frauds", "Online Shopping Frauds"], "correctAnswer": "Banking Frauds" },
    { "id": 27, "questionText": "To safeguard ourselves from online fraud, we must:", "options": ["Regularly update your banking passwords and PIN of the debit/credit cards.", "Never share your bank and credit card details such as your online account password, card number, PIN, OTP, etc. with anyone.", "Always check the website URL starts with HTTPS.", "All of the above"], "correctAnswer": "All of the above" },
    { "id": 28, "questionText": "What does 'Maintain Authenticity' mean in using Social Media?", "options": ["Never post anything personal.", "Always pretend to be someone else.", "We must be honest about our identity. Never pretend to be someone else.", "Only post about professional life."], "correctAnswer": "We must be honest about our identity. Never pretend to be someone else." },
    { "id": 29, "questionText": "What does 'Always use a disclaimer' mean in using Social Media?", "options": ["Always share personal views without mentioning they are yours.", "While sharing personal views about something, we must make it clear that these are personal views.", "Never share personal views.", "Always use a formal tone."], "correctAnswer": "While sharing personal views about something, we must make it clear that these are personal views." },
    { "id": 30, "questionText": "What is 'Intellectual Property Rights' (IPR)?", "options": ["Rights over physical property.", "Legal property rights for a person over creations of his/her mind.", "Rights over natural resources.", "Rights to vote."], "correctAnswer": "Legal property rights for a person over creations of his/her mind." },
    { "id": 31, "questionText": "Which of the following is a type of Intellectual Property Rights?", "options": ["Copyright", "Patent", "Trademark", "All of the above"], "correctAnswer": "All of the above" },
    { "id": 32, "questionText": "What is 'Copyright'?", "options": ["It gives an inventor the exclusive right to make, use, and sell his or her work for a specific time period.", "It is a symbol, word or logo legally registered or established and used as representing a company or a product.", "It is the legal right given exclusively to the person for a fixed number of years to publish and record the literary, artistic, musical, or musical use of his or her work.", "It is the right to prevent others from using one's invention."], "correctAnswer": "It is the legal right given exclusively to the person for a fixed number of years to publish and record the literary, artistic, musical, or musical use of his or her work." },
    { "id": 33, "questionText": "What is 'Patent'?", "options": ["It is the legal right to publish and record literary work.", "It is a symbol, word or logo.", "It is the right that gives an inventor the complete right to make, use, and sell his or her work for a specific time period.", "It is the right to prevent plagiarism."], "correctAnswer": "It is the right that gives an inventor the complete right to make, use, and sell his or her work for a specific time period." },
    { "id": 34, "questionText": "What is 'Trademark'?", "options": ["It is the legal right to publish and record literary work.", "It is the right that gives an inventor the complete right to make, use, and sell his or her work.", "It is a symbol, word or logo legally registered or established and used as representing a company or a product.", "It is the right to prevent software piracy."], "correctAnswer": "It is a symbol, word or logo legally registered or established and used as representing a company or a product." },
    { "id": 35, "questionText": "What is 'Plagiarism'?", "options": ["Creating original work.", "Citing sources correctly.", "Refers to the usage or imitation of the language and thoughts of another person projected as one's original work.", "Collaborating on a project."], "correctAnswer": "Refers to the usage or imitation of the language and thoughts of another person projected as one's original work." },
    { "id": 36, "questionText": "Which of the following is a way to prevent plagiarism?", "options": ["Use Citation-Citation refers to acknowledging the original writer and the source from where the material has been taken.", "Rephrase the matter.", "Use \"\" for statements quoted by another person.", "All of the above"], "correctAnswer": "All of the above" },
    { "id": 37, "questionText": "A virus is a type of software or malware that spreads between several computers and corrupts data. Which of the following is a sign of a virus attack?", "options": ["The system runs faster.", "Unwanted pop-ups that repeatedly appear.", "The computer automatically shuts down.", "Both b and c."], "correctAnswer": "Both b and c." },
    { "id": 38, "questionText": "What is 'Cyber Safety'?", "options": ["The use of the internet without any rules.", "The practice of sharing all personal information online.", "Refers to the safe and responsible use of the Internet to safeguard one's personal information while not misusing anyone else's personal information.", "The process of hacking into secure networks."], "correctAnswer": "Refers to the safe and responsible use of the Internet to safeguard one's personal information while not misusing anyone else's personal information." },
    { "id": 39, "questionText": "Which of the following is a safety measure to use while using the Internet or computer?", "options": ["Install the most recent antivirus software on your computer.", "Use caution when entering your password on the internet.", "Do not respond to shady emails or strangers.", "All of the above"], "correctAnswer": "All of the above" },
    { "id": 40, "questionText": "What is 'Ethical Hacking'?", "options": ["Illegal hacking activities.", "Hacking for personal gain.", "This technique for national security, creating safer systems, etc. This is known as ethical hacking.", "Destroying computer systems."], "correctAnswer": "This technique for national security, creating safer systems, etc. This is known as ethical hacking." },
    { "id": 41, "questionText": "Digital footprints are the impression we leave through a foot or walking on the ground while moving. In the same way, a digital footprint is a trail of data of a user that he leaves while using the Internet. What is a 'Digital Footprint'?", "options": ["Physical evidence left behind.", "A trail of data a user leaves while using the Internet.", "Information stored on a local computer.", "Encrypted data."], "correctAnswer": "A trail of data a user leaves while using the Internet." },
    { "id": 42, "questionText": "What is the Internet also called?", "options": ["Networks", "Computers", "Mobiles", "The Network of Networks"], "correctAnswer": "The Network of Networks" },
    { "id": 43, "questionText": "Studying from home through the Internet is called:", "options": ["I-learning", "E-Learning", "C-Learning", "None of these"], "correctAnswer": "E-Learning" },
    { "id": 44, "questionText": "A digital footprint is also known as:", "options": ["Digital Diary", "Digital Dossier", "Database", "None of these"], "correctAnswer": "Digital Dossier" },
    { "id": 45, "questionText": "Why do hackers break into the other's computer system?", "options": ["To steal important data", "To destroy the system", "Both a and b", "To help others"], "correctAnswer": "Both a and b" },
    { "id": 46, "questionText": "Crimes that are committed through the Internet are called:", "options": ["Fiber crimes", "Internet crimes", "Cyber crimes", "None of these"], "correctAnswer": "Cyber crimes" },
    { "id": 47, "questionText": "Spamming refers to:", "options": ["Sending an email from an unidentified source", "Sending wrong information", "Sending bulk of information", "Sending an email from an unidentified source, sending wrong information, sending bulk of information."], "correctAnswer": "Sending bulk of information" },
    { "id": 48, "questionText": "We can adopt the following measures to avoid spam:", "options": ["Preview your message before opening them", "Don't click on spam email", "Both a and b", "None of these"], "correctAnswer": "Both a and b" },
    { "id": 49, "questionText": "We can adopt the following measures to avoid email hacking:", "options": ["Keep changing your passwords", "Keep updating your operating system", "Don't plug into devices you are not sure about", "All of these"], "correctAnswer": "All of these" },
    { "id": 50, "questionText": "The technique used by cybercriminals to attain information from individuals is called:", "options": ["Cyber bullying", "Cyber troll", "Social engineering", "All of these"], "correctAnswer": "Social engineering" }
  ],
  "Entrepreneurship in Digital Age": [
    { "id": 1, "questionText": "Which of the following is defined as the promotion of concept, value proposition, and quality assurance?", "options": ["Business Plan", "Digital Marketing", "Entrepreneurship", "Promotion"], "correctAnswer": "Promotion" },
    { "id": 2, "questionText": "Entrepreneurship gives people the tools to create and impact the world. What does entrepreneurship enable?", "options": ["Individual wealth only", "Creating new products only", "Individuals to provide the situations for entrepreneurs to emerge and develop.", "Working for established companies."], "correctAnswer": "Individuals to provide the situations for entrepreneurs to emerge and develop." },
    { "id": 3, "questionText": "Digital marketing is also called online marketing. It is the promotion of brands to connect with potential customers using the internet and other forms of digital communication. Which of the following is true about Digital Marketing?", "options": ["It only uses traditional media.", "It is a physical store promotion.", "It is also called online marketing.", "It focuses on local customers only."], "correctAnswer": "It is also called online marketing." },
    { "id": 4, "questionText": "Digital marketing includes which of the following?", "options": ["Email marketing", "Social media", "Web-based advertising", "All of the above"], "correctAnswer": "All of the above" },
    { "id": 5, "questionText": "In digital marketing, promotion refers to any type of marketing communication used to inform target audiences of the relative merits of a product, service, brand, or issue, most of the time persuasive in nature. Which of the following describes Promotion?", "options": ["Only advertising", "Only sales", "Any marketing communication to inform target audiences", "Only public relations"], "correctAnswer": "Any marketing communication to inform target audiences" },
    { "id": 6, "questionText": "A simple statement that summarises why a customer would choose your product or service is called a:", "options": ["Business Overview", "Marketing Strategy", "Value Proposition", "Mission Statement"], "correctAnswer": "Value Proposition" },
    { "id": 7, "questionText": "What is a way of preventing mistakes and defects in manufactured products, services and avoiding problems when delivering products or services to customers?", "options": ["Value Proposition", "Marketing Plan", "Quality Assurance", "Project Management"], "correctAnswer": "Quality Assurance" },
    { "id": 8, "questionText": "What does a digital marketing plan provide a wide variety of ways for marketing managers to engage upcoming customers?", "options": ["A financial plan", "A human resources plan", "A roadmap for engaging customers", "A legal compliance plan"], "correctAnswer": "A roadmap for engaging customers" },
    { "id": 9, "questionText": "Online advertising is the bidding and buying of appropriate ad units on third-party sites, such as display ads on blogs, mediums, and other relevant websites. Which of the following is a component of a digital marketing plan?", "options": ["Content Marketing", "SEO", "Advertising Online", "Social Media Marketing"], "correctAnswer": "Advertising Online" },
    { "id": 10, "questionText": "Content marketing is an important strategy for attracting potential customers. What is 'Content Marketing'?", "options": ["Paid advertising only.", "Social media posts only.", "Publishing a regular high-quality, relevant content online to help you establish a connection with your customers.", "Email newsletters only."], "correctAnswer": "Publishing a regular high-quality, relevant content online to help you establish a connection with your customers." },
    { "id": 11, "questionText": "SEO (Search Engine Optimisation) is the process of showing your business on the first page of Search Engines' results. What is 'SEO'?", "options": ["Social media marketing", "Paid advertising", "Search Engine Optimisation", "Email marketing"], "correctAnswer": "Search Engine Optimisation" },
    { "id": 12, "questionText": "Which of the following is a social media platform used for digital marketing?", "options": ["Instagram", "Twitter", "YouTube", "All of the above"], "correctAnswer": "All of the above" },
    { "id": 13, "questionText": "Instagram is a great opportunity for businesses and brand owners to improve their content and increase its visibility across all Instagram pages. What is Instagram's role in digital marketing?", "options": ["It is primarily for private use.", "It is a paid advertising platform only.", "It helps improve content and increase visibility across Instagram pages.", "It is for short videos only."], "correctAnswer": "It helps improve content and increase visibility across Instagram pages." },
    { "id": 14, "questionText": "Twitter is most renowned for its real-time updates. It is one of the easiest places to create a group of like-minded people. What is Twitter's role in digital marketing?", "options": ["Primarily for long-form content.", "Provides a convenient platform for sharing blogs and YouTube videos.", "Exclusively for visual content.", "Used for formal business communication only."], "correctAnswer": "Provides a convenient platform for sharing blogs and YouTube videos." },
    { "id": 15, "questionText": "YouTube can benefit you from YouTube's access to Google's advertising network by placing YouTube advertisements. What is YouTube's role in digital marketing?", "options": ["It is for text-based content only.", "It places YouTube advertisements using Google's advertising network.", "It is a platform for image sharing.", "It only hosts live streams."], "correctAnswer": "It places YouTube advertisements using Google's advertising network." },
    { "id": 16, "questionText": "Facebook is the most popular social media website that can connect you with billions of customers and offer key information about your business, products, services, and upcoming events. What is Facebook's role in digital marketing?", "options": ["Limited to personal communication.", "Connects with billions of customers and offers business information.", "Only used for professional networking.", "Primarily for advertising campaigns."], "correctAnswer": "Connects with billions of customers and offers business information." },
    { "id": 17, "questionText": "A business plan is a document setting out a business's future objectives and strategies for achieving them. What is a 'Business Plan'?", "options": ["A financial report only.", "A marketing strategy only.", "A document setting out future objectives and strategies.", "A daily task list."], "correctAnswer": "A document setting out future objectives and strategies." },
    { "id": 18, "questionText": "The essential components of a business plan are as follows:", "options": ["Executive Summary", "Business Overview", "Products and Service Design", "All of the above"], "correctAnswer": "All of the above" },
    { "id": 19, "questionText": "What is an 'Executive Summary' in a business plan?", "options": ["Detailed financial projections.", "The entire business plan is summarised in the executive.", "A list of all products.", "A marketing strategy."], "correctAnswer": "The entire business plan is summarised in the executive." },
    { "id": 20, "questionText": "An overview of the company's goods and services is included in this section of a business plan. Which of the following is true about 'Business Overview'?", "options": ["It focuses on sales targets.", "It details employee responsibilities.", "It includes information on products that consumers' concerns are understood, built, and improved.", "It outlines legal compliance."], "correctAnswer": "It includes information on products that consumers' concerns are understood, built, and improved." },
    { "id": 21, "questionText": "We must determine whether the company service or product has a greater possibility than current options of meeting a market need. Which component of a business plan is this?", "options": ["Operations", "Marketing", "Market Need", "Business Overview"], "correctAnswer": "Market Need" },
    { "id": 22, "questionText": "Investors will find the operations portion of your business plan useful. This section gives a detailed explanation of your workflow as well as the goals, objectives, and processes of your firm. Which component of a business plan is this?", "options": ["Market Need", "Marketing", "Operations", "Executive Summary"], "correctAnswer": "Operations" },
    { "id": 23, "questionText": "You need to research your competitors to understand their strengths and weaknesses. Which component of a business plan is this?", "options": ["Operations", "Marketing", "Market Need", "Costing"], "correctAnswer": "Marketing" },
    { "id": 24, "questionText": "To implement the business plan, you must address the budget. It describes the balance sheets, funding, cash flow statements, and profit and loss statements, among other things. Which component of a business plan is this?", "options": ["Marketing", "Operations", "Costing", "Project Management"], "correctAnswer": "Costing" },
    { "id": 25, "questionText": "Media literacy tools help people develop approachable media capability to critically analyze messages, offers opportunities for learners to expand their experience of media, and help them develop generative media proficiency to increase creative skills in making their own media messages. What is 'Media Literacy'?", "options": ["The ability to create media.", "The ability to read media.", "The ability to critically analyze and understand media messages.", "The ability to sell media."], "correctAnswer": "The ability to critically analyze and understand media messages." },
    { "id": 26, "questionText": "Project management is crucial since it guarantees that the project is being followed properly. Some of the things guaranteed by project management tools are very important and useful in a business plan. What is 'Project Management'?", "options": ["Managing daily tasks.", "Financial planning.", "Ensuring a project is followed properly with set objectives.", "Customer relationship management."], "correctAnswer": "Ensuring a project is followed properly with set objectives." },
    { "id": 27, "questionText": "What is a 'Transaction'?", "options": ["The act of receiving something.", "The act of selling something.", "An instance of buying or selling something.", "An agreement between a buyer and a seller."], "correctAnswer": "An instance of buying or selling something." },
    { "id": 28, "questionText": "What is 'Payment'?", "options": ["The process of selling something.", "The process of buying something.", "The processing of a payment from a Payer to a Payee.", "The exchange of products."], "correctAnswer": "The processing of a payment from a Payer to a Payee." },
    { "id": 29, "questionText": "Which of the following is an example of a transaction?", "options": ["The act of selling something", "The act of agreement between a buyer and a seller is referred to as a transaction", "The amount of money exchanged for products and services", "All of the above"], "correctAnswer": "The act of agreement between a buyer and a seller is referred to as a transaction" },
    { "id": 30, "questionText": "Which of the following is an example of a payment method?", "options": ["Debit cards", "Credit cards", "Bank transfers", "All of the above"], "correctAnswer": "All of the above" },
    { "id": 31, "questionText": "Which digital marketing platform is for professional networking?", "options": ["Facebook", "Quora", "LinkedIn", "Instagram"], "correctAnswer": "LinkedIn" },
    { "id": 32, "questionText": "Which digital marketing platform focuses on question-and-answer content?", "options": ["Facebook", "Quora", "LinkedIn", "Instagram"], "correctAnswer": "Quora" },
    { "id": 33, "questionText": "Which digital marketing platform is for sharing blogs and articles?", "options": ["Facebook", "LinkedIn", "Our Blog", "Twitter"], "correctAnswer": "Our Blog" },
    { "id": 34, "questionText": "Which digital marketing platform is for video content?", "options": ["Twitter", "YouTube", "Instagram", "Tumblr"], "correctAnswer": "YouTube" },
    { "id": 35, "questionText": "Which digital marketing platform is for image and short video sharing?", "options": ["LinkedIn", "Instagram", "Twitter", "Tumblr"], "correctAnswer": "Instagram" },
    { "id": 36, "questionText": "Which digital marketing platform is known for microblogging and real-time updates?", "options": ["LinkedIn", "Instagram", "Twitter", "Tumblr"], "correctAnswer": "Twitter" },
    { "id": 37, "questionText": "Which digital marketing platform is for sharing short-form content, often images or GIFs?", "options": ["LinkedIn", "Instagram", "Twitter", "Tumblr"], "correctAnswer": "Tumblr" },
    { "id": 38, "questionText": "Entrepreneurship refers to the convenience of launching a _____ online.", "options": ["Business", "Education", "Shopping", "Program"], "correctAnswer": "Business" },
    { "id": 39, "questionText": "Which of the following is also referred to as digital Marketing?", "options": ["Online Banking", "Online Shopping", "Online Marketing", "All of these"], "correctAnswer": "Online Marketing" },
    { "id": 40, "questionText": "The _____ process also involves identifying a potential market, assessing the size of the market, and determining an approximate estimate of the product's value.", "options": ["Costing", "Market need", "Operations", "Marketing"], "correctAnswer": "Market need" },
    { "id": 41, "questionText": "Video marketing enables companies to connect with customers in a more _____ engaging and cooperating way.", "options": ["Tastefully", "Audible", "Visually", "None of these"], "correctAnswer": "Visually" },
    { "id": 42, "questionText": "The entire business plan is _____ in the executive summary.", "options": ["Copied", "Summarised", "Deleted", "Shared"], "correctAnswer": "Summarised" },
    { "id": 43, "questionText": "The _____ is an instance of buying or selling something.", "options": ["Transaction", "Payment", "Sharing", "Storing"], "correctAnswer": "Transaction" },
    { "id": 44, "questionText": "Digital Marketing is also called online marketing.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "True" },
    { "id": 45, "questionText": "The way to prevent mistakes is called quality assurance.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "True" },
    { "id": 46, "questionText": "Advertisement is not a component of digital marketing.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "False" },
    { "id": 47, "questionText": "Email is not used for Marketing.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "False" },
    { "id": 48, "questionText": "Paid Search increases the visibility of Search Engine.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "True" },
    { "id": 49, "questionText": "Hashtags help people to find your tweets.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "True" },
    { "id": 50, "questionText": "A business plan is a document setting out an objective of the business.", "options": ["True", "False"], "correctAnswer": "True" }
]
}
export const shortQuestions = {
    "Emerging Technologies": shortQuestionsData.slice(0, 2),
    "Data Communication and Computer Networks": shortQuestionsData.slice(2, 4),
    "Microsoft Excel": shortQuestionsData.slice(4, 6),
    "Google Sheets": shortQuestionsData.slice(6, 8),
    "Computational Thinking": shortQuestionsData.slice(8, 10),
    "Programming": shortQuestionsData.slice(10, 12),
    "Digital Citizenship": shortQuestionsData.slice(12, 14),
    "Entrepreneurship in Digital Age": shortQuestionsData.slice(14, 16),
};

export const longQuestions = {
    "Emerging Technologies": longQuestionsData.slice(0, 1),
    "Data Communication and Computer Networks": longQuestionsData.slice(1, 2),
    "Microsoft Excel": longQuestionsData.slice(2, 3),
    "Google Sheets": longQuestionsData.slice(3, 4),
    "Computational Thinking": longQuestionsData.slice(4, 5),
    "Programming": longQuestionsData.slice(5, 6),
    "Digital Citizenship": longQuestionsData.slice(6, 7),
    "Entrepreneurship in Digital Age": longQuestionsData.slice(7, 8),
};
